Lowell Thomas Film Collection
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
- 9. Nepal, 1949-1969; 240 cans
  - Hazy Temples (Eeotica) God Monsters at End, 1949; 126 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 946)
    The film showed buildings structures, birds, people walking by and it showed statues.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - Gertz Mos Kat. Temples, 181 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 947)
    The film showed a lot of people in dressed in traditional Indian garments and it showed something burning. The film also showed buildings and statues.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - Gertz Mos Religion, 1949; 161 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 948)
    The film showed people sitting down, showed people lighting candles and it showed them praying.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - Gertz Mos Religion- Living Godess, 124 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 949)
    The film showed four men carrying a girl in carriage and it showed a lot of people walking. It also showed people sitting down.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - Namche Bazaar House Blessing Folk Dance, 1949; 345 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 951)
    The audio plays Asian music and singing.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - LT + Father Moran on steps, fountain boys sing, 1950; 153 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 956)
    Young boys wearing uniforms singing together outside. Lowell Thomas speaks to the group.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - LT + Father Moran, Bad Soond, 1950; 234 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 957)
    Lowell Thomas sitting with a priest outside and speaking to the camera.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - LT Father Moran (Trk) Bad sound, 235 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 958)
    Audio of Lowell Thomas speaking with Father Moran (poor quality sound).; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - R8, D49 Gywakil Spinning Yak Wool, 1949; 26 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 970)
    Women weave baskets together outside.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - Rumjung Inside House, Plowing Field, 47 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 973)
    Sounds of a man plowing his field with two cattle.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - Inside Sherpa House; RHUMJUNG, 76 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 974)
    "Wild sounds." Audio of people in the village. Speaking voices come from inside a house.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio:; Type:
  - Mos G Eagle Soaring, 1949; 222 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 994)
    The film showed houses, mountains, people carrying things on their back, it showed children and it showed animals.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - Namche Bazaar, 1949; 285 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 995)
    The film showed people walking and standing around. It showed a lot of people doing things and putting things in a bag.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - Namache Bazaar, 1949; 233 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 996)
    The film showed a man putting up flag poles, showed people carrying things, and it showed people herding different type of animals.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - Durrance Mos Fig Kritipur, 1949; 354 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 997)
    The film showed people walking up and down a hill carrying things and it showed houses, trees and a dog.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - Gertz Mos Kat. Fest Big Wheel Parade with Tree Contraption, 1949; 91 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 999)
    Film of a busy street filled with kids and people gathered to watch an event. The presentation of a "tree contraption" in a parade.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - Father Moran + LT intv., 1953; 120 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 1094)
    On the audio track you can hear Lowell Thomas talking about the land of lost horizon and to a priest about young men being in the military and how he came up from India and they talked about Nepal. You can hear children singing; Format: 16mm; Picture:; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - Father Moran + LT intv., 1953; 78 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 1095)
    The film showed Lowell Thomas sitting down with a priest talking; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - LT & Father Moran on Steps Fountain Boys Sing "Pope", 1950; 76 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 1096)
    On the audio track you can hear children singing and you also hear two men talking.; Format: 16mm; Picture:; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - LT & Father Moran on Steps Fountain Boys Sing "Pope", 1950; 76 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 1097)
    The film showed children sitting down singing and showed two children playing a piano and playing drum. The film also showed a Lowell Thomas talking to another guy; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - LT & Father Moran on Steps Fountain Boys Sing, 1950; 165 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 1098)
    On the audio track you can hear a little boy singing and then you hear a group of boys singing. You also hear men talking about singing group and talking about father Miller; Format: 16mm; Picture:; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - D-80 Namche Bazaar TR-1, House Blessing HH0378-0917, To HH1420, 289 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 1120)
    Recording of a Namche family blessing. Men chanting and playing instruments; Format: 16mm; Picture:; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - D-80 Namche Bazaar TR-1, House Blessing HH0378-0917, To HH1420, 192 linear feet 1 400ft (16mm) (Can 1121)
    Footage of a Namche house blessing. People playing instruments and singing.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - Nepal, 670 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1240)
    Chanting and birds chirping.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio: Optical; Type: Optical
  - Nepal Music, 757 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1241)
    Rustling and an animal growling.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio: Optical; Type: Optical
  - Nepal FX, 870 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1242)
    Sound efffects: clanging, rushing river, Namche crowd, single chirp, Sherpa hut and pots and pans, yaks walk out, crowd talking, very low chanting, water running and splashing, animal grunting while people yell with rustling in the background, people shouting over each other in a non-English language, and a rooster crowing. Multiple takes of a Vidal Sassoon commercial for Protein 21 shampoo used as slugs.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio: Optical, Magnetic; Type: Optical, Magnetic
  - Nepal FX, 951 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1243)
    Dogs barking and birds honking, men talking in a non-English language, crackling, animal snorting, possibly water rushing, and an elephant trumpeting.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio: Optical, Magnetic; Type: Optical, Magnetic
  - Nepal FX, 845 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1244)
    Bird noises; a chrashing thump;squeaking mechanical noise; two thumps; talking; loud noise and a man screaming; crowd of voices; birds chirping; Swagamb tourists; Shiva Ratri- fat woman (babbling water or someone swimming); and a loud crowd.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio: Optical, Magnetic; Type: Optical, Magnetic
  - Nepal FX, 699 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1245)
    Bell ringing; man chanting/singing; crowd speaking; splashing water (likely swimming, maybe rowing); and a loud crowd.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio: Optical, Magnetic; Type: Optical, Magnetic
  - Nepal, 1951; 559 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1246)
    "Return to Shang-Ri-La" with Lowell Thomas. [Title frame not there, but marked on film at 53 ft.] An elderly Lowell Thomas in the region near Tibet, witnessing its people's brightly-colored outfits, its architecture, and people bathing in the river.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - Nepal, 1951; 654 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1247)
    Students walk in a line over a dirt hill. They make their way to the entrance of a small village. Lowell Thomas stands with three men and addresses the camera. Toddlers wander around while adults herd the strays back to the group. We see women sitting around and making yarn. Men and women of the village perform a dance. Men use goats to help them plow the dirt. The children walk to school. We see them sitting in their classroom listening to their teacher. The village gathers for a celebration of singing and playing drums. Monks are seen on a hilltop. The monks sit together playing instruments and writing on parchment. They come out of a building wearing costumes. Cut to men filling up syringes with liquid supplements. A man approaches a sleeping/dead elephant in the tall Savannah grass. We see shots of several village people wearing different traditional outfits and makeup. Lowell Thomas addressed the camera once more. A man plays the violin and sings.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - Nepal, 825 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1248)
    Lowell Thomas talking to men in a Tibetan refugee village outside of Kathmandu, Nepal; different groups of people chanting and singing songs in call and response; drums; wind instrument melody; crackling sound (possibly water); discussing tranquilizing a rhino; two men talking in an unidentified language; bird noises with peoples' voices and barking dogs in teh background; a single gunshot; mention of a pink membrane; and leaving the "land of Shangri-la".; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio: Optical, Magnetic; Type: Optical, Magnetic
  - Nepal Music, 1950; 1000 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1249)
    Band playing "---" while people talk; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio: Optical, Magnetic; Type: Optical, Magnetic
  - Nepal Music, 555 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1250)
    Scenes with optical audio: bulldozer, three people in a room, and a classroom scene with music.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio: Optical; Type: Optical
  - Nepal Music, 662 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1251)
    Nepal Music Track Roll C; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Optical, Magnetic; Type: Optical, Magnetic
  - Nepal Narration, 997 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1252)
    Lowell Thomas narrating a show on Nepal. He first visits the Tengboche Buddhist Monastery in Khumjung, Nepal at the foot of Mt. Everest after passing through the Namche Bazaar. He then visits the Terai jungle of Nepal with Dr. King to capture a baby one-horned rhino for the Miami Zoo.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - Nepal sound effects, 512 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1253)
    Audio of tones, sounds and vibrations repeated.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - Organ/Chanting, 527 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1254)
    On the audio track you can hear singing (chanting) and an organ, a drum and other instruments being played.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - Nepal, 865 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1255)
    Lowell Thomas announces his journey to Shang-ri La in Nepal. He gives a short background on the country and its wonders as well as the events that his journey will consist of; the royal wedding of the crown prince, the Hindu festival celebrating Shiva's birthday, and a journey into the wild in search of a one-horned rhino. Before the royal wedding he describes the culture of the people and during the wedding he gives a live description of what is taking place. Thomas explains the Hindu festival before hand and the film ends as he's headed towards it.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - Good Jungle Bird Effects, 508 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1256)
    Ambient nature sounds and birds chirping. The man recording audio yawns loudly a few times. He speaks up and begins documenting his hunting experience. On the second day of the hunt they captured a rhino. They are now looking for a female rhino.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - Nepal Reel 1, 569 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1257)
    Audio of Lowell Thomas speaking. We hear clips of him talking about different locations. Cut to him interviewing a man. They speak about farming and yaks.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio: Optical, Magnetic; Type: Optical, Magnetic
  - Slow Sitar, Sitar Fast, Song, Music B R-1 Nepal, 438 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1258)
    On the audio track you can hear music and instruments being played and you also hear a woman singing.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - Woman weaving on loom HD, Trimming hat, Misc., D-51 Old man sorting wool, Women chanting/ + Group w/spinning, D-51 Men and women weaving, wool., 920 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1259)
    On the audio track you can hear a man saying that women and men are weaving and the sounds are of children rolling up yarn and men were making hats.The man was describing what the people were doing and what they wear wearing. You also can hear people singing and chanting. He also was saying what kind shots were being taken.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - Wild SD. for D-14, Engagement Ceremony D-14, Soldiers Commands National Anthem, 318 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1260)
    On the audio track you can hear a man saying the recordings are of an engagement ceremony of a Royal Prince and his wife to be. You can hear music laying and the man saying what was happening and you hear guns going off in the background.; Format: 16mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - Cap. Cities Broadcasting Rolls 5C-11C Rolls 12C, 13C, 14C Can #15, 1968; 1013 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1261)
    The film showed people sitting down talking, it showed a dog running around, it showed a bird in a tree, it showed men carrying bananas, it showed a woman looking up on something, it showed pigs and it showed people walking. The film showed smoke, it showed people putting things on helicopter and it showed the helicopter taking off and showed people waving. The film showed in house, it showed people cooking and eating.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - Nepal, 1952; 869 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1262)
    Return To Shangri-LA with Lowell Thomas, written by Robert Hertzberg and produced by Milton Fruchtman and Narrated by Lowell Thomas was about life in Nepal. It showed precession before a wedding ceremony, it showed an ancient hindu wedding ceremony, it showed people honoring and praying to the gods, it showed children learning and it showed the hunt for a baby Rhino. Directed and photographed by Dick Durrance; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio: Optical; Type: Optical
  - Nepal, 1952; 1005 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1263)
    see 1957.26A for description; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio: Optical; Type: Optical
  - The Crowning of King Mahendra in Katmandu, 844 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1264)
    Lowell Thomas witnesses the coronation of King Mahendra in Kathmandu, Nepal. Narrated by Lowell Thomas. Contains "The End" slide, but beginning missing.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio: Optical; Type: Optical
  - Capitol Cities Nepal- Can #5, Can #1, Roll 6-13, 1949; 972 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1265)
    Men clean and paint buildings while people on the street below sell their wares to those walking past with bundles on their backs. People crowd the streets to watch painted elephants walk past and in a nice courtyard, richly dressed people eat from a buffet while a military band plays. There is a scene of a man playing a string instrument and singing and many other scenes depicting the snow-capped mountains in the distance.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - Kathmandu Soaltee Hotel, 1969; 743 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1266)
    Street performers entertain a crowd. Shots of a Tibetan marketplace. The camera follows different people walking around the market.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - Gertz Mos Kathmandu General II, 725 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1267)
    The film showed a man cutting another man facial hair. it showed a lot of people walking around, it showed people carrying things, it showed a man riding a bicycle, it showed people washing clothes, it showed people working, it showed someone passing things out, it showed children walking around, it showed people riding on animals, it showed people selling materials and it showed fishes.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - Kathmandu General 1&2, 1949; 503 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1268)
    Marketplace in Tibet. Barbers cut people's hair on the front steps of a building. We follow people walking around the market.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - Durrance Hunt Camp, Terai Scenics, elephants in water, Nepal, Camp El in water, 718 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1269)
    The film showed men riding on elephants, then the elephants laid down in water and the men were splashing water on the elephants. The film showed other men on elephants in a forested area. It showed boys bending some type of bushes and binding them together. It showed a crowd of animal and it showed people walking and sitting down.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - High Adventure Theatrical RII Mus B, 1961; 684 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1532)
    Audio: Indian music plays with women singing along. Cut to men chanting. Music plays at a parade. A sitar is played.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color, Black & White; Audio: Optical, Magnetic; Type: Optical, Magnetic
  - Namche Bazaar House Blessing Folk Dance, 1949; 455 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1534)
    The film showed a man waiting to clap his hand and it showed six people dancing, a man playing an instrument and it showed children sitting down watching and it showed other people standing up. It showed a woman passing out and then it showed men and children sitting down. Three of the men were holding wired objects in the their hands.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - Capital City Comm Bessie Jones 2 of 4, Shiua Ratel People in City, Camp, 1953; 590 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1537)
    Hundreds of people pray bath themselves and their family members in a stream before crowing around an entrance, guarded by police, trying to get into a string of buildings. The end of the film shows people walking down the street stopping to buy things from vendors parked alongside the road.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - Shiva Ratri Bathing in River, 1949; 710 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1538)
    The film showed a man smoking, it showed people washing clothes and bathing themselves. The film showed people walking around and carrying things on their head. It showed people sitting down and it showed tents.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - Gertz Saiva Ratri People & Camp, 1949; 522 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1539)
    The film showed people walking around, sitting down, carrying things on their head and showed a lot of people doing different things. The film showed people cooking and it showed buying and selling things.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - unlabeled, 1969; 556 linear feet 1 1200ft (16mm) (Can 1558)
    On a dirt road where people walk with bundles on their backs and stop to buy things from others who've laid their wares out on the side of the street, groups of men clean and repaint buildings and signs. Soldiers in bright red uniforms line up in an open square while an elephants is decorated in the same bright red. A courtyard full of nicely dressed people look on as a man, similarly dressed, pins something to a line of people, inciting applause from the crowd. In between these scenes are landscape views of a mountain range and the river that runs through it.; Format: 16mm; Picture: Color; Audio:; Type:
  - Nepal, 2630 linear feet 1 2000ft (35mm) (Can 1730)
    Lowell Thomas describes his experience in Nepal. Tibetan refugees build a life in the villages of Nepal. Describes the life of the Sherpa and their moral codes. Lowell goes on an adventure to capture a rare one horned rhino to bring back to the United States.; Format: 35mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - Nepal, 1952; 2480 linear feet 1 2000ft (35mm) (Can 1731)
    On the audio track you hear Lowell Thomas talking about the land of Nepal, talks about the royal wedding, talks about the Hindu Kingdom and the birthplace of the Hindu gods. He narrates the what was going on in the city and at the wedding.; Format: 35mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - L Thomas "High Adventure", 1954; 1642 linear feet 1 2000ft (35mm) (Can 1732)
    Lowell Thomas narrates the royal wedding procession in Kathmandu, Nepal, including the dancers and people who had traveled from all over the country. From the wedding, he goes to search for the one-horn rhino and narrates as the men surround, tranquilize, and move the rhino back to camp.; Format: 35mm; Picture: Color; Audio: Optical, Magnetic; Type: Optical, Magnetic
  - Nepal Heavy Crowd, Eerie Wind, Loop 15 Shiva Rdtri-Water #, Big Crowd, Loop #1 Pottery Square, Loop #5 Carridge with Couple, Loop #12 Walla-Walla, Loop #13 Chiva Ratri Water #, Loop #3 Small Groap Childan, Chiva Ratri Crowd, 261 linear feet 1 1000ft (35mm) (Can 2979)
    The audio records crowd noise, children playing, rushing water, and hooves.; Format: 35mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - Loop 14 stream, 17, loop 6 Terai sunrise Birds, loop 5 couple leaving Singha Durbar, loop 8 wind, loop 7 jungle birds, loop 4 parade crowd, loop 27 elephant snorts, loop 12 Walla Walla, loop 16 birds I, loop 10 heavy crowd, 179 linear feet 1 1000ft (35mm) (Can 2980)
    The audio records birds and other animals, crowd noise, and people talking.; Format: 35mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - Shiva Ratri Water, Loop #17 Birds II, Loop #3 Small Group Children, 188 linear feet 1 1000ft (35mm) (Can 2981)
    Sounds of rushing water. Birds chirping and wild sounds. Music from India. Sounds from a wild elephant.; Format: 35mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - Loop #2 Small Group, Loop #8 Jungle Birds (Stronger) Nepal, Nepal Birds, Circus Crowd, 510 linear feet 1 1000ft (35mm) (Can 2982)
    On the audio track you can hear noises and sounds of people talking in the background.; Format: 35mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - Elephants in Brush, parade big Katmanda, Eerie Wind, Birds Nepal, Sunrise Birds, Tigers, 195 linear feet 1 1000ft (35mm) (Can 2983)
    The audio records a tiger, rustling leaves, and bird sounds.; Format: 35mm; Picture: N/A - Audio track only; Audio: Magnetic; Type: Magnetic
  - High Adventure - Nepal, 1954; 857 linear feet 1 1000ft (35mm) (Can 2984)
    The film showed Lowell Thomas with other people in India. The film was narrated by Lowell Thomas and he took part in a wedding ceremony for the prince and crowned princess. It showed Lowell Thomas on an elephant with other men. They went on a hunt to capture a rhino.; Format: 35mm; Picture: Color; Audio: Optical; Type: Optical
  - Nepal Barrel Trims + Outs Mixed, 1958; linear feet 1 1000ft (35mm) (Can 2985)